Dr. Olga O. Bochkareva

Date of Birth: Sept. 10, 1988

Address: 1030 Faculty of Life Sciences, University of Vienna,

Djerassiplatz 1, Vienna, Austria

E-mail: olga.bochkareva@univie.ac.at

Mobile phone: +43 664 88326272

Languages: English (fluent), German (A1-A2), Russian (native)

Web page (personal): https://www.bochkareva.me/

ORCID (incl. Publications): 0000-0003-1006-6639

Research interests:

My research interests cover various topics of microbial genomics with the large focus to genome organization and evolution, genotype-to-phenotype connection, and host-microbe interraction. I'm developing new computational methods for microbial genome analysis and apply them to fundamental and applied scientific problems.

Work experience:

2023 – *present* senior postdoc, CUBE, Centre for Microbiology and Environmental Systems Science, University of Vienna, Austria.

2019 – 2023 postdoctoral researcher, Institute of Science and Technology (ISTA), Austria. Prof. Fyodor Kondrashov group.

2017- 2019 junior research scientist, Department of Life Sciences, Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology, Moscow, Russia. Prof. Mikhail Gelfand group.

2012- 2019 junior research scientist, Kharkevich Institute for Information Transmission Problems RAS, Moscow, Russia. Prof. Mikhail Gelfand group.

Education:

2012–2019 Ph.D., Kharkevich Institute for Information Transmission Problems RAS. PhD thesis: *"Reconstruction of evolutionary history of genome rearrangements in bacteria"*, Supervisor: *Prof. Mikhail S. Gelfand.*

2010–2012 Master of Science (applied mathematics and physics), Department of Molecular and Biological Physics, Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology. Master thesis "Bacterial microevolution and genome rearrangements", Supervisor: Prof. Mikhail S. Gelfand.

2005–2010 Bachelor of Science (applied mathematics and physics), Department of Molecular and Biological Physics, Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology.

Funding and Awards:

2023 ESPRIT Programme ("Early Stage Programme: Research, Innovation and Training"), funding from **Austrian Science Fund**, total amount – **294.015€**.

2019 ISTplus postdoctoral fellowship. Funding from the **European Union's Horizon 2020** research and innovation programme under the Marie Skłodowska-Curie grant agreement No 754411

Publications:

8 peer-reviewed publications, 3 first and 3 last authorships

(* - equal contribution)

- Maximilian Baumgartner, Rebecca Zirnbauer, Sabine Schlager, Daniel Mertens, Nikolaus Gasche, Barbara Sladek, Craig Herbold, Olga Bochkareva, Vera Emelianenko, Harald Vogelsang, Michaela Lang, Anton Klotz, Birgit Moik, Athanasios Makristathis, David Berry, Stefanie Dabsch, Vineeta Khare & Christoph Gasche. Atypical enteropathogenic E. coli are associated with disease activity in ulcerative colitis Gut Microbes, 2022, Nov 22; 14(1):2143218 https://doi.org/10.1080/19490976.2022.2143218
- 2. Natalia O Dranenko, Maria Tutukina, Mikhail S. Gelfand, Fyodor Kondrashov & **Olga O Bochkareva (last authorship)** Chromosome-encoded IpaH ubiquitin ligases indicate non-human pathogenic *Escherichia* **SciRep** 2022 Apr 27, 12:6868 doi: 10.1038/s41598-022-10827-3
- 3. Alexey Zabelkin, Yulia Yakovleva, **Olga Bochkareva*** & Nikita Alexeev*. PaReBrick: PArallel REarrangements and BReaks identification toolkit. **Bioinformatics** 2021 Oct 03; 38(2):357-363 https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btab691
- 4. Zaira Seferbekova, Alexey Zabelkin, Yulia Yakovleva, Robert Afasizhev, Nikita Alexeev, Mikhail S Gelfand & **Olga O Bochkareva.** High rates of genome rearrangements and pathogenicity of *Shigella* spp. **Frontiers Microbiology** 2021 Apr 12; 12:831. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2021.628622
- 5. Olga Sigalova, Andrei V Chaplin, **Olga O Bochkareva**, Pavel V Shelyakin, Vsevolod A Filaretov, Evgeny E Akkuratov, Valentina Burskaya & Mikhail S Gelfand. *Chlamydia* pan-genomic analysis reveals balance between host adaptation and selective pressure to genome reduction. **BMC Genomics.** 2019 Sep 12;20(1):710. doi: 10.1186/s12864-019-6059-5.
- 6. Pavel V Shelyakin*, **Olga O Bochkareva***, Anna A Karan & Mikhail S Gelfand. Micro-evolution of three *Streptococcus* species: selection, antigenic variation, and horizontal gene inflow. **BMC Evol. Biol.** 2019. Mar 27;19(1):83. doi: 10.1186/s12862-019-1403-6.
- 7. **Olga O Bochkareva**, Elena V Moroz, lakov I Davydov & Mikhail S Gelfand. Genome rearrangements and selection in multi-chromosome bacteria *Burkholderia* spp. **BMC Genomics**. 2018 Dec 27;19(1):965. doi: 10.1186/s12864-018-5245-1.
- 8. **Olga O Bochkareva**, Natalia O Dranenko, Elena S Ocheredko, German M Kanevsky, Yaroslav N Lozinsky, Vera A Khalaycheva, Irena I Artamonova & Mikhail S Gelfand. Genome rearrangements and phylogeny reconstruction in *Yersinia pestis*. **PeerJ**. 2018 Mar 27;6:e4545. doi: 10.7717/peerj.4545.

Preprints and submitted papers:

- Natalia O Dranenko, Aleksandra D Rodina, Yaroslav V Demenchuk, Mikhail S. Gelfand & Olga O Bochkareva. Evolutionary trajectories of secondary replicons in multipartite genomes bioRxiv 2023 Apr 09: 536151; doi:10.1101/2023.04.09.536151
- Alper Yurtseven, Sofia Buyanova, Amay A. Agrawal, Olga O. Bochkareva & Olga V. Kalinina Machine learning and phylogenetic analysis improves predicting antibiotic resistance in *M. tuberculosis* bioRxiv 2023 Sept 06:556328

Papers in preparation:

- Ekaterina V. Vostokova, Natalia O. Dranenko, Mikhail S. Gelfand, **Olga O. Bochkareva**. Genome rearrangements and host adaptation in *Wolbachia*
- Alexey Zabelkin & Olga O. Bochkareva. BADLON: linear collinear Blocks Analysis: Distribution, Location, and compositiON
- K. Jain, R. Hauschild, **O. Bochkareva**, R. Roemhild, C. Guet Conservation of start codon controls expression dynamics of mar operon

Invited Talks

- 1. Computational identification and biological interpretation of genome rearrangements in microbes **2023 2nd Young AMICI Symposium** organized by University of Vienna, Austria (online)
- 2. Detection of genome rearrangements responsible for bacterial phenotype switching. **2022 Helmholtz Institute for Pharmaceutical Research Saarland (HIPS)** Saarland, Germany
- 3. How bacteria switch to dark side. 2022 SMTB'22 University of Tartu, Tartu, Estonia
- **4.** Microbes: taxonomy, genome structure and molecular evolution **2022** workshop organized by **Institute of Bioinformatics (online)**
- 5. Role of genome rearrangements in formation of bacterial phenotypes, **2021 EMBL**, **Heidelberg** Germany
- Comparative genomics of prokaryotes (cookbook), 2020 Summer School of Bioinformatics Institute, online
- 7. Structure and evolution of bacterial chromosomes **2019 Bioinformatics Institute** Open Lectures series, St. Petersburg, Russia
- 8. Comparative genomics of prokaryotes (cookbook), **2019** workshop organized by **Bioinformatics Institute**, St. Petersburg, Russia

Conference Talks:

- 1. Evolutonary trajectories of secondary replicons in bacteria **FEMS'23** Humburg, Germany
- 2. Detection of genome rearrangements responsible for bacterial phenotype switching. **SASBi'22** Stellenbosch, South Africa
- 3. Evolutionary benefits of bacterial genomes with chromids MCCMB'21 Moscow, Russia
- 4. Genome rearrangements in bacteria. **BiATA'19** St. Petersburg, Russia
- 5. Evolution of bacterial chromosomes. **Chromosome'18** Novosibirsk, Russia

Supervised students:

2023 Bogdan Sotnikov, Vera Rubinova, Bioinformatics Institute. Russia. Term project

"Non-canonical start codons and where to find them "

2022 Ekaterina Vostokova, Skoltech, Russia. Co-advising **Master project**

"Evolution of Wolbachia genomes." co-PI: Mikhail Gelfand.

2021 Ariadna Semenova, Moscow State University, Russia. Term project

"Insertion sequences in B. mallei: adaptation to intracellular lifestyle"

2020 Yulia Yakovleva, Alexey Zabelkin Bioinformatics Institute, Russia. Term project

"PaReBrick: PArallel REarrangements and BReakpoints identification toolkit" (published in Bioinformatics)

2020 Kristina Perevoshchikova, Moscow State University, Russia. Term project

"Evolutionary benefits of bacterial genomes with chromids"

2019 Zaira Seferbekova, Moscow State University, Russia. **Term project**

"Impact of mobile elements into pathogenicity of Shigella" (published in Frontiers Microbiology)

2019 Moldir Zhiyenbayeva, graduate student at HSE, Moscow, Russia. Co-advising **Master project** "Comparative Genomics of Bacillus spp.". co-PI: Mikhail Gelfand.

2018 Natalia Dranenko, graduate student at MIPT, Moscow, Russia. Co-advising **Bachelor project** "Reconstruction of OxyR ancestor sequence in bacteria". co-PI: Mikhail Gelfand.

Cooperation partners:

2023-present Prof. David Berry, University of Vienna, Vienna, **Austria**. Project: Identification of shafflons in gut microbiomes.

2022-present Prof. Fyodor Kondrashov, OIST, Okinawa, **Japan**. Project: Selection forces in multipartite bacterial genomes.

2022-present Prof. Calin Guet IST Austria, Klosterneuburg, **Austria**. Project: Conservation of non-canonical start codons in mar operon genes.

2022-present Prof. Olga Kalinina, Helmholtz Institute for Pharmazeutical Research Saarland (HIPS), **Germany**. Project: Machine learning and phylogenetic analysis improves predicting antibiotic resistance in *M. tuberculosis*

2021-present Prof. Dan I. Andersson, Uppsala University, **Sweden.** Project: Fitness effects of short random peptides.

2020-2022 Dr. Nikita Alexeev, ITMO University, Saint Petersburg, **Russia**. Project: Development of the bioinformatic toolkit for whole-genome analysis.

2020-2022 Prof. Christoph Gasche, Medical University of Vienna, Vienna, **Austria**. Project: Genetic factors under biofilms formation in pathogenic *E.coli*.

2016-2018 Prof. Marc Robinson-Rechavi, Evolutionary Bioinformatics Lab, Department of Ecology and Evolution, Université de Lausanne, Lausanne, **Switzerland**. Project: Positive selection and horizontal gene transfer in prokaryotes.

2010-2014 Prof. Pavel Pevzner, University of California at San Diego, California, **USA**. Project: Application of the MGRA (Multiple Genome Rearrangements and Ancestors) algorithm to microbial data.

Teaching experience:

Fall 2020 "Comparative genomics of prokaryotes", Lecturer/course instructor

course for master and PhD students (Bioinformatics Institute, St Petersburg, Russia), in Russian. Final evaluation by students: 9.3 out of 10 (the highest evaluation across all courses during the term)

Spring 2019 "Bioinformatics", co-instructor

course for master and PhD students (Skoltech, Moscow, Russia), in English

Autumn 2018 "Comparative Genomics", co-instructor

course for master and PhD students (joint program Skoltech/HSE, Moscow, Russia), in English

2011-2014 Math teacher, School 463, Moscow, Russia

Services for the scientific community and volunteering

1. Summer School of Theoretical and Molecular Biology

recruiting project leaders, lecturers and course instructors; design of lectures and courses; management of courses execution and labs; and moderation of scientific discussions;

2. Bioinformatics Institute

giving open lectures and workshops for broad audience interested in bioinformatics

3. Member of <u>Scholars-without-borders</u> programme:

for students and academics from Ukraine, Belarus or Russia who have been affected by the war

4. Reviewer

for Microbial Genomics, BMC Genomics, Frontiers Microbiology